<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>JA</title>
    <link>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://arnoldjulian.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>JA</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/media/icon_huec113d82bc1f20423ec7da4ca4804812_85793_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>JA</title>
      <link>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning phases of matter</title>
      <link>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/project/phase_transitions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/project/phase_transitions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;short-description&#34;&gt;Short description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identifying phase transitions and classifying phases of matter is central to understanding the properties
and behavior of a broad range of material systems. While many-body systems have a large number of degrees of freedom,
their phases are usually characterized by a small set of physical quantities like response functions or order parameters.
However, the identification of phases and the transitions between them generally involves a large state space, requiring
lots of intuition and knowledge about the underlying physical system. In this project, we develop and analyze machine-learning
methods to perform these tasks in a data-driven manner. Such methods can aid in the identification of unexplored phase transitions
as well as the discovery of new phases of matter.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning molecular collisions</title>
      <link>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/project/molecular_collisions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/project/molecular_collisions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;short-description&#34;&gt;Short description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Predicting the outcomes of chemical reactions is one of the essential tasks for efficient material design and engineering. However, the exhaustive characterization of reactions at the microscopic state-to-state level quickly becomes computationally intractable using conventional approaches due to the rapid growth of the underlying state space. This is particularly restricting for the study of reactive gas flow at high temperatures, such as hypersonic flow around a space vehicle reentering the atmosphere, because a large number of states and transitions between them are accessible under such conditions. In addition, experimental data is scarce and the system is inherently nonequilibrium. In this project, we tackle this problem by training coarse-grained neural network-based surrogate models given data from ab initio reference simulations which predict the changes in energy and state population distributions upon collision.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Entropy production in ticking clocks</title>
      <link>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/project/ticking_clocks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/project/ticking_clocks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;short-description&#34;&gt;Short description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of time and its role in physics, in particular quantum theory, remains an
active field of research. The process of timekeeping is linked to the usage of clocks
as reference systems. Thus, many open questions about time can be addressed
through the study of these devices. Ticking clocks provide information about the flow
of time in terms of discrete ``ticking&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; events. In this project, we study autonomous
ticking clocks based on a model derived from axiomatic principles. We try to
answer the question whether the theory of quantum information imposes any
constraints on the relation between the entropy production per tick of a ticking clock
and its accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
