<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>PSC 1001: Introduction to Comparative Politics | JA</title>
    <link>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/courses/psc1001/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://arnoldjulian.github.io/courses/psc1001/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>PSC 1001: Introduction to Comparative Politics</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>PSC 1001: Introduction to Comparative Politics</title>
      <link>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/courses/psc1001/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative Politics and the Comparative Method</title>
      <link>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/courses/psc1001/week1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/courses/psc1001/week1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;content&#34;&gt;Content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;module 1.1&lt;/strong&gt;, we will be discussing an overview of comparative politics. First, we will talk about some of the most important theoretical perspectives in the discipline, emphasizing the role of institutions in politics. Second, we will discuss the important elements of an explanation in political science: independent variables, dependent variables and causal mechanisms. You will complete a causal diagram exercise with a partner to practice this concept.Third, we’ll talk about the difference between correlation and causation, or in other words how variables are sometimes related to one another through a causal relationship whereas at other times the relationship between two variables is purely spurious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;module 1.2&lt;/strong&gt;, we will be discussing the comparative method. In this module we’ll be looking at the role of hypotheses in comparative politics and how they can be tested using a handful of simple methodological tools that harness variation in independent and dependent variables across country or regional cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both modules you will be reading relevant articles and textbook chapters, as well as watch lecture and supporting videos that relay important information about the concepts listed above. You will then take a quiz to ensure you have understood what you read. These quizzes will help prepare you for the final exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objectives&#34;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of unit, you should be able to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explain the difference between an independent and dependent variable. (Course objective 1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demonstrate how “causal mechanisms” link independent and dependent variables. (Course objectives 1, 2, &amp;amp; 4)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devise an appropriate test for whether a causal relationship between a dependent and independent variable exists. (Course objective 6)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-slides&#34;&gt;Lecture Slides&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emmanuelteitelbaum.com/slides/psc1001_1.1/#/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; title=&#34;Slides&#34;&gt;Module 1.1 Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emmanuelteitelbaum.com/slides/psc1001_1.2/#/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; title=&#34;Slides&#34;&gt;Module 1.2 Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>States, State Capacity and State Fragility</title>
      <link>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/courses/psc1001/week2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/courses/psc1001/week2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;content&#34;&gt;Content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;module 2.1&lt;/strong&gt;, we will be discussing state capacity and state building. We will begin our discussion by addressing some basic definitional questions about states. First of all, what is a state? How is this concept used in the field of comparative politics and how should we define it? What does it mean to say that a state has more or less capacity? What aspects of state capacity are we most concerned with in our analysis of modern nation-states? Finally, what does it mean to say that a state is ‘fragile’ or that a state has ‘failed’? What are some examples of failed states and what are some the implications of state failure and fragility?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;module 2.2&lt;/strong&gt; we will continue with our discussion of state capacity and asking why some states are stronger than others. We will start with the rise of the modern state in Europe, where we will focus on Charles Tilly’s analysis of Europe. We will then move on to state building in Africa, where we broaden our scope beyond the western European experience. You will complete a Two-by-Two diagram to help you compare and analyze two states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both modules you will be reading relevant articles and textbook chapters, as well as watch lecture and supporting videos that relay important information about the concepts listed above. You will then take a quiz to ensure you have understood what you read. These quizzes will help prepare you for the final exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objectives&#34;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of unit, you should be able to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identify the basic functions of a state. (Course objectives 1, 3, &amp;amp; 4)
Identify measures of state capacity. (Course objectives 1, 3, &amp;amp; 4)
Analyze the relationship between a state and its citizens. (Course objectives 1, 3, &amp;amp; 4)
Explain why some states fail while others succeed. (Course objectives 3, 4, &amp;amp; 6)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-slides&#34;&gt;Lecture Slides&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emmanuelteitelbaum.com/slides/psc1001_2.1/#/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; title=&#34;Slides&#34;&gt;Module 2.1 Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emmanuelteitelbaum.com/slides/psc1001_2.2/#/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; title=&#34;Slides&#34;&gt;Module 2.2 Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>States, State Capacity and State Fragility</title>
      <link>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/courses/psc1001/week3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/courses/psc1001/week3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;content&#34;&gt;Content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;module 3.1&lt;/strong&gt;,  we will be covering the concepts of “ethnicity” and “nationalism” and asking how these two concepts impact political and economic outcomes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;module 3.2&lt;/strong&gt; we will focus on institutional solutions to conflict in divided societies. First, we’ll expand upon our discussion in the last lecture about how ethnicity and exclusion give rise to civil conflict. Then, we will talk about constitutional design and how the right set of political institutions might help to alleviate conflict. We will introduce two contrasting theories of constitutional design for divided societies&amp;ndash;consociationalism and centripetalism. You will complete a Most Similar Systems Design to analyze these concepts in regards to analyzing if political institutions can be used to manage ethnic diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both modules, you will be reading relevant articles and textbook chapters, as well as watching lectures and supporting videos that relay important information about the concepts listed above. You will then take a quiz to ensure you have understood what you read. These quizzes will help prepare you for the final exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objectives&#34;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of unit, you should be able to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the concept of “ethnicity”. (Course objectives 1 &amp;amp; 3)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the concept of “nationalism”. (Course objectives 1 &amp;amp; 3)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify the root causes of ethnic conflict in developing countries. (Course objectives 1, 3, &amp;amp; 4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discuss potential policy solutions to reduce tensions between ethnic groups. (Course objectives 1, 3, 4, &amp;amp; 6)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explain the link between ethnic diversity and public goods provisioning. (Course objectives 1, 3, &amp;amp; 4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-slides&#34;&gt;Lecture Slides&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emmanuelteitelbaum.com/slides/psc1001_3.1/#/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; title=&#34;Slides&#34;&gt;Module 3.1 Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emmanuelteitelbaum.com/slides/psc1001_3.2/#/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; title=&#34;Slides&#34;&gt;Module 3.2 Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>States, State Capacity and State Fragility</title>
      <link>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/courses/psc1001/week4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/courses/psc1001/week4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;content&#34;&gt;Content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;module 4.1&lt;/strong&gt; we are going to be talking about regime type, trends in democracy, and the “third wave” of democratization that brought free and fair elections, as well as civil liberties, to many countries in the developing world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;module 4.2&lt;/strong&gt; we’ll talk about authoritarian and hybrid regimes and how they differ from democracies. We’ll look closely at the case of Russia and countries in the Middle East to better understand how nondemocratic regimes work in practice.  You will develop a Most Different Design System to analyze the causes of democracy, and specifically why some countries are democracies while others remain authoritarian or hybrid regimes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both modules you will be reading relevant articles and textbook chapters, as well as watch lecture and supporting videos that relay important information about the concepts listed above. You will then take a quiz to ensure you have understood what you read. These quizzes will prepare you for the final exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objectives&#34;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of unit, you should be able to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify the difference between democratic, authoritarian, and hybrid regimes. (Course objectives 1, 3, &amp;amp; 5)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyze the stability of democratic and authoritarian regimes. (Course objectives 1, 3, 4, &amp;amp; 5)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the concept of “democratic consolidation”. (Course objectives 1 &amp;amp; 3)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyze the causes of democratic backsliding. (Course objectives (1, 3, &amp;amp; 4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-slides&#34;&gt;Lecture Slides&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emmanuelteitelbaum.com/slides/psc1001_4.1/#/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; title=&#34;Slides&#34;&gt;Module 4.1 Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emmanuelteitelbaum.com/slides/psc1001_4.2/#/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; title=&#34;Slides&#34;&gt;Module 4.2 Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Women and Politics</title>
      <link>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/courses/psc1001/week5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/courses/psc1001/week5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;content&#34;&gt;Content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;module 5.1&lt;/strong&gt; we will begin our discussion of equal representation and women’s role in politics. We&amp;rsquo;ll discuss trends in female representation over time and talk a little bit about what accounts for these trends. In our discussion, we’ll pay special attention to the role of gender quotas in boosting female representation. You will do this by completing a Scatter Plot. The purpose of this exercise is to  encourage you to think about some of the economic factors related to unequal representation and to teach you how to illustrate relationships between variables using a scatter plot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;module 5.2&lt;/strong&gt; we are going to focus on descriptive representation as it pertains to gender. First we are going to ask how descriptive representation is achieved through gender quotas. Then we will look at how descriptive representation influences a leader’s policy preferences. Finally, we will look at how descriptive representation influences public policy.
In both modules you will be reading relevant articles and textbook chapters, as well as watch lecture and supporting videos that relay important information about the concepts listed above. You will then take a quiz to ensure you have understood what you read. These quizzes will prepare you for the final exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objectives&#34;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of unit, you should be able to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyze why women are more represented in some countries relative to others. (Course objectives 1, 3, &amp;amp; 4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discuss changes in women’s representation over time. (Course objectives 1, 3, 4, &amp;amp; 6)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify the effects of women’s representation on policy. (Course objectives 1, 3, &amp;amp; 4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyze the cultural effects of women’s leadership. (Course objectives 1, 3, &amp;amp; 4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-slides&#34;&gt;Lecture Slides&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emmanuelteitelbaum.com/slides/psc1001_5.1/#/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; title=&#34;Slides&#34;&gt;Module 5.1 Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emmanuelteitelbaum.com/slides/psc1001_5.2/#/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; title=&#34;Slides&#34;&gt;Module 5.2 Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Political Economy</title>
      <link>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/courses/psc1001/week6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arnoldjulian.github.io/courses/psc1001/week6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;content&#34;&gt;Content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;module 6.1&lt;/strong&gt; we are going to be looking at the political economy of the welfare state and, in the next module, we will talk about institutions and economic development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;module 6.2&lt;/strong&gt; we will consider the causes of economic growth and development and how a country’s regime type (whether it is authoritarian or democratic) relates to development outcomes. Here you will complete a Data Mapping exercise. The purpose of this exercise is to encourage you to think about economic trends in the BRICS nations and to illustrate these trends using the IMF Data Mapper tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both modules you will be reading relevant articles and textbook chapters, as well as watch lecture and supporting videos that relay important information about the concepts listed above. You will then take a quiz to ensure you have understood what you read. These quizzes will prepare you for the final exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objectives&#34;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of unit, you should be able to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define “social democracy”. (Course objective 1)
Identify the ways that social democracies differ from other wealthy democracies. (Course objectives 1, 3, &amp;amp; 4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define and compare “economic growth” and “human development”. (Course objectives 1, 3, &amp;amp; 4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify the drivers of growth and development. (Course objectives 1 &amp;amp; 4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyze the effects of globalization on domestic politics. (Course objectives 1, 3, &amp;amp; 4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-slides&#34;&gt;Lecture Slides&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emmanuelteitelbaum.com/slides/psc1001_6.1/#/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; title=&#34;Slides&#34;&gt;Module 6.1 Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emmanuelteitelbaum.com/slides/psc1001_6.2/#/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; title=&#34;Slides&#34;&gt;Module 6.2 Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
